Guide to the University College Senior Theses MC 24
New York University Archives
University College Senior Theses
Bulk, 1897-1925
1897-1934
MC 24
New York University Archives
2.0 linear feet (4 boxes)
From 1894 through 1925, graduation requirements for students enrolled in the University College of Arts and Pure Science at New York University included the completion of a prescribed number of courses and the presentation of a "satisfactory thesis" on a subject selected by students in December of their senior year and approved by the faculty. The thesis related to one of the studies of a student's major field. The collection consists of 100 senior theses, 1897-1925, and one honors thesis in History, 1934.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into one series:
University College Senior Theses
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 100 senior theses, 1897-1925, and one honors thesis in history, 1934. The collection highlights student reactions to topics of the times, such as the Spanish-American War, women's suffrage, race issues, World War I, and immigration policies. On the whole, the collection provides a sample of undergraduate student research and writing in the early decades of the twentieth century.
History of the Senior Thesis Requirement at the University College of Arts and Pure Science
From 1894 through 1925, graduation requirements for students enrolled in the University College of Arts and Pure Science at New York University included the completion of a prescribed number of courses and the presentation of a "Satisfactory thesis" on a subject selected by students in December of their senior year and approved by the faculty. The thesis related to one of the studies of a student's major field. Upon successful completion of the thesis, the student received either his B.A., B.S., or (from 1893-1902) a Ph.B. degree. By 1925, the thesis requirement had been abandoned, but students were now given the opportunity of selecting an honors program.
Honors students announced their intentions at the end of the sophomore, or beginning of the junior year. At the time of declaration, students had to have an overall "B" average and could not receive more than one grade below a "B." For the senior year of the honors student, a thesis was also required in a subject relevant to the department in which honors was sought.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Provenance
On July 2, 1981, Professor Carl Prince presented eighteen of the theses to Professor Bayrd Still. In 1985, the remaining theses were given to archivist Tom Frusciano.
New York University. Faculty. 20th century.; New York University. Students. 20th century.; New York University.; Washington Square College of Arts and Science.; New York (N.Y.) |x Intellectual lif |y 20th century.; theses.
- Series I: University College Senior Theses
  - Godfrey, A.W., "The Hanseatic League", 1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Orr, David, "The Belgian Revolution of 1830: An Historical Study", March 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Skene, Fred, "The Efficiency of the Police Force During Riots", 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gorton, James Treat, "Jean Baptiste de Lemark: His Life and Work", March 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Waldman, Morris D., "The National Guard of France", April 1898 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cooperstock, John, "The Effects of Irrigation on Civilization in the West", March 1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hatch, Nelson B., "Toryism in the Episcopal Church During the American Revolution", March 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lichtenstein, Walter, "The 'Great Families' of New York", March 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mendel, Philip, "The Negro Question", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Otis, Isaac L., "The Development of the American State Constitutions Particularly of Massachusetts from the English Trading Company Charters", April 1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Raymond, Walter Buchanan, "The Political Future of the Philippines", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Altman, Joseph, "History of the Origin of the North West Ordinance", Apr 1900 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Elder, Jr., Robert Duncan, "Industrial Co-operation as Illustrated by the Familistere Society of Guise, France", 1900 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Addy, Jr., Richard C, "The Labor Question in the Philippine Islands", Apr 1901 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hadley, Jr., Samuel Hopkins, "Religious Movements for Social Betterment", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rickaby, Hamilton C., "The Attitude of the States toward the Virginia and Kentucky Resolutions", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Stockell, Victor Holles, "The History of the Attitude of the United States towards the Establishment of a Permanent International Court of Arbitration", Mar 1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wallin, William, "The Intent and Application of the second portion of Section One of the Fourteenth Amendment to the Constitution of the United States", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chapin, Newton, "Causes and Motives of the Burr Conspiracy", 1902 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kohn, Jacob, "The Beginnings of a Philosophy of History in Vico", 1902 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dawson, Richard B., "The New York Clearing House", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Friedman, Nathan M., "The Attitude of the United States Government Towards International Arbitration during the decade - 1899-1909", Apr 1909 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rowland, Ralph Wright, "Woman Suffrage: An Outline of Legislative Enactments in the United States", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bruster, Ralph R., "The History of the Working Out of the Association of 1774", 1912 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elliffe, Jr., Richard E., "A Brief History of Partisan Warfare In Westchester County During the 'American Revolution", 1912 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fleischer, Morris Bernard, "The Political Aspects of the Trial and Prosecution of Aaron Burr", Apr 1912 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rosenbaum, Louis, "The Law and Practice of the Enlistment of Negro Soldiers in the Northern Army during the Civil War", Apr 1912 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Underwood, Horace H., "America's Part in Maintaining the Integrity of China", 1912 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Berney, Abraham Arthur, "Private Financial Aid Rendered to the Federal Government in the Civil War", Apr 1913 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Conklin, F. Colwell, "The Diplomatic Relations of the United States and France During the Civil War", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Edelman, Isador, "The Ethics of Nietzsche", Apr 1913 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Guernsey, Irwin Scofield, "The Personal Participation by Polk in Diplomatic Relations with Mexico during his Administration", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hamilton, Jr., William Henry, "The History and Present Status of the Sherman Anti-Trust Law", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Kaplan, Abraham D., "The Influence of Anson Burlingame, American, As Ambassador To and From the Chinese Empire", May 1913 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Lindenbeerg, Alexander, "Lucian and His Imitators", Apr 1913 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - McAndrew, Hurlbert, "The Effect of the Blockade on the Cotton Industry of the South during the Civil War", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - McClure, Carl, "French Government Aid to the Revolutionists before the Recognition of Independence", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Nixon, Albert B., "The Effect of Domicile in Determining Enemy Character in Time of War", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Pfeffer, Max D., "The Disappearance of Serfdom in England", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Ripperger, C. Wesley, "The History of the Attitude of the United States Towards the Exemption from Capture of all Private Property at Sea in Time of War", Apr 1913 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Rosenstein, Filbert, "The Jew as an American Immigrant", Apr 1913 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Roth, M., "Official Interference with the Fugitive Slave -Law between the years 1850-1860", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Seed, Henry George, "A Comparison-of English and American Newspapers of the Present Day with Respect to Space Allotment and Mechanical Make Up", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Taylor, George E., "A History of the Struggle to Retain Kentucky in the Union in 1861", Apr 1913 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Bosniak, Jacob, "History of the Jews in France in the End of the 13th Century", Apr 1914 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Demarest, Stanley T., "Dutch Colonization in New York as Portrayed by Washington Irving", 1914 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Gold, A.D., "A Study In The Attitude of Rabelais toward Pope as shown in the Fourth Book of 'Pantagruel'", 1914 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Gordon, H.Z., "The Reorganization of Germany by Napoleon", Apr 1914 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Hammond, Oscar W., "Rise of England as a Sea Power in the Seventeenth Century", 1914 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Lavenburg, Israel, "England's Attitude toward the Right of Search", Apr 1914 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Levy, I. Alfred, "Battle of Marathon", 1914 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Margulies, Joseph H., "The History of the Vulgate Translation of the Bible", Apr 1914 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Marks, James Garland, "The History of President Lincoln's Order Suspending the Writ of Habeas Corpus During the Civil War", Apr 1914 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Volk, Frank R., "Comparison of the Two Tragedies by Corneille, Horace and Pertharite", Apr 1914 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Doye, Robit W., "The Diplomatic Relations Involved In the Marriage of Catherine of Aragon with Prince Arthur and with Henry VIII", Apr 1915 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Kohl, Frank E. and Edward A. Sears, "An Investigation of the Possibilities of the Photographic Plane Perspective Method of Topographic Surveying with Special Reference to Small Land Area", 1915 (Box 3, Folder 55.1)
  - Marra, Ubaldo J., "The French Element in the American Colonies Prior to the Revolution", Apr 1915 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Rogoff, Samuel, "Albert Gallatin and the Negotiation of the Treaty of Ghent", Apr 1915 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Smith, O.N., "Problems in the Glaciation of New York State", Apr 1915 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Draper, William H., "The Great War and some of its Effects on America and the other Neutrals", 1916 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Jame, Joseph, "The Development of the Jury System-in England During the Middle Ages", Apr 1916 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Schulte Jr., Theodore E., "The History of the United States' Attitude Toward the Transfer to Neutral Flag of Belligerent Merchant Vessels", Apr 1916 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Coane, Clarence B., "Our War Exports", 1917 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Edelman, George I., "Cracow, Posen or Warsaw: Which Policy for Poland?", Apr 1917 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Cremer, Charles Morton, "The Baltic Provinces of Russia in Retrospect and Prospect", 1919 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Cunliffe, Grant Wilfred, "Political and Intellectual Tendancies of Modern France", May 1919 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Finley, Harold Brooks, "Effect of the Mineral Resources of Europe Upon the Balance of Power", May 1919 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Foss, Fremont C., "Relations Between Germany and Russia 1904 To 1910", May 1919 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Traina, Salvatore, "Morocco and the Peace of Europe (1900 - 1910), 1919 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Greeman, Edward, "Citizen Genet's Appeal to the American People", Apr 1920 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Jame, David, "The Political Agitation of the Non- Franchised Against the Corn Laws in England", 1920 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Stuart, Robert Brown, "The Development of the Government of Canada from 1860 - 1914", 1920 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Van Aken, Roy, "The Attitude of South America Towards the Monroe Doctrine", 1920 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Van Arnain, Philip E., "Conscription in the Confederate States", 1920 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Falk, Solomon, "Opposition to the Early American Stage Prior to 1800", Apr 1921 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Hauser, Frederick Howard, "Attempts at the Re- Organization of Macedonia (1910 - 1920)", May 1921 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Joseph, Ben M., "The 1922 Coal Strike and the Miner's Case", Apr 1922 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Millen, Thomas MacDougall, "The Government Operation of Railroads in the United States During the - Period of the Great War", 1922 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Anderson, George Valentine, "The Social Principles of Joseph Chamberlain", Apr 1923 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Cochran, Thomas C., "A Brief History of Field Tactics as Developed by Marlborough, Fredrich, Napoleon and Von Moltke", 1923 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Edsall, Preston W., "Hospitality to Prizes in Neutral Ports", 1923 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Hill, Huntington, "The Pichegru Conspiracy of 1803-04", Apr 1923 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Gray Jr., Hamilton,"The Present Immigration Policy", 1924 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Johnsen, T. Norman, "The Moroccan Question", 1924 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Lyon, John T., "James Russell Lowell and the Anti- Slavery Movement", 1924 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Bartley, John Cowgill, "Cuba's Relation to Our Foreign Policy Prior to the American Civil War", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Berkson, William R., "The Federal Courts Before the United States Supreme Court", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Beylegaard, Reidar G., "The Granger Movement and State Regulations", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Eichler, Herbert, "The Dispersion of the Loyalists of the American Revolution", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Good, Alexander, "Disraeli's Vacillations in Parliamentary Reform", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Jablanka, Frank A., "The Development of the Office of the Attorney General of the United States after the Adoption of the Constitution", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Maggio, Vincent S., "The Girondins and the Conduct of the War, March 1792 - March 1793", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Mallon, Arthur, "The Organization and Administration of the War Department During the Revolutionary War", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - McGovern, Clarence Francis, "The Mexican Policy of President Woodrow Wilson", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Mendelson, Irving Howard, "Lincoln and Chase: A Study of Political Management" ', Jan 1925 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Quigley, John Joseph, "The Influence of the Atlantic Seaboard Upon American History In Its Formative Period", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Rosenberg, Sidney Robert, "A History of Landlord and Tenant", 1925 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Schofield, Ellwood M., "The Great Awakening of 1740: An Epoch in American Church History", Jun 1925 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Smoleroff, Julius W., "The Opinions of Lord Randolph Churchill", May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Yaroshevitch, R., "The Russian Decembrist Rebellion," honors thesis in history, University College, 1934, May 1925 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Tilone, Robert, "The Non-Slaveholding Whites of the Antebellum South", April 1934 (Box 4, Folder 100)